# RAUL FIOL

### CLOUD ENGINEER

CONTACT
437-973-8357
raulfiol93@gmail.com
www.raulfiol.me
North York, Toronto
SKILLS
Cloud Kubernetes IaC Linux CI/CD Python Data Engineering
CERTIFICATIONS
AWS Solutions Architect Associate
AWS Solutions Architect Professional
EDUCATION
Telecommunications and Electronics Engineering
Universidad Tecnológica de La Habana
2012 - 2017
LANGUAGES
Spanish
English —
Franch

#### PROFILE

I'm a Telecommunications Engineer become a Cloud Solutions Architect, with over 6 years of experience in the IT world. I'm all about building cloud and on-premise infrastructure using Infrastructure as Code and CI/CD tools. When I'm not busy being a Python and Bash enthusiast, you can find me working on my software development skills and adding 'Ops' to everything.

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

### **Research Assistant**

Centennial College, Applied Research, Innovation and Entrepreneurship Services (ARIES) Jan 2023 - Feb 2023

- Developed a high-volume production process for IoT device initialization in batches, automating drive and image cloning with Clonezilla and implementing IoT Fleet Management with JFrog Connect, increasing the production to more than 200 devices provisioned per week.
- Conducted research on IoT technologies and their potential applications in different fields.

# **Cloud Data Engineer**

General Software Inc.

Aug 2021 - Sept 2022

- Designed, built, and maintained Big Data pipelines using Gitlab, Terraform, Bash, Google Cloud Build, Azure DevOps, and AWS CodeBuild, resulting in about a 25% reduction in data processing time.
- Developed a serverless cloud service architecture using Python, Google Cloud Functions, AWS Lambda, Azure Functions, and SQL for data ingestion and wrangling, increasing the efficiency of the process by a huge margin.
- Utilized distributed parallel batch and streaming data processing and transformation with Python and cloud services such as Google Cloud Dataflow, Apache Beam, Apache Kafka, Pub/Sub, and SQS, resulting in data processing speed.
- Created Data Lakes and Data Warehouses as data sinks for further processing and analysis using Google Cloud Storage, Google Big Lake, AWS S3, Azure Data Lake, BigQuery, Redshift, and Azure Synapse Analytics, resulting in a 20% increase in data availability and analysis.

## **Cloud Data Center Engineer**

**ETECSA** 

Oct 2018 - Aug 2021

- Oversaw the deployment and management of virtualized infrastructure using VMware vSphere, Huawei Fusion Sphere OpenStack, and VMware Cloud Director, enabling faster provisioning and scaling of resources for development and testing teams.
- Implemented Kubernetes clusters for container orchestration and management, improving the deployment and scalability of microservices-based applications.
- Collaborated with development teams to create testing, delivery, and deployment pipelines using AWS, GCP, and Azure, resulting in faster and more efficient delivery of internal and user-facing applications.
- Conducted regular audits of infrastructure and applications to identify and address security vulnerabilities, ensuring compliance with industry standards and best practices.
- Automated the physical IT infrastructure administration using Terraform, Ansible, Bash, and Python scripting, resulting in a 40% increase in efficiency and time savings.
- Adopted GitOps for infrastructure deployment using GitLab self-hosted, resulting in a 50% reduction in deployment time.

#### Communications/IT Solutions Architect Jr

**EPROYIV** 

Sept 2017 - Oct 2018

- Architected traditional telephony communications networks, reducing downtime.
- Designed and implemented IT infrastructure and network design for client needs, resulting in increase of customer satisfaction.
- Architected security systems for fire and intrusion detection, improving overall security and compliance standards.